<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rwby on bheisler.github.io</title>
    <link>https://bheisler.github.io/tags/rwby/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rwby on bheisler.github.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://bheisler.github.io/tags/rwby/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Penny&#39;s Sword - RWBY - Part 2</title>
      <link>https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 19:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Salutations! Welcome to the second part of my post on my replica of Penny&amp;rsquo;s
Sword from Rooster Teeth&amp;rsquo;s animated web show RWBY. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read &lt;a href=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part1/&#34;&gt;part
1&lt;/a&gt;, go ahead and check it out. When we left
off, most of the parts were shaped and primed but not yet assembled. This time
we&amp;rsquo;ll get into the painting, and some of it might be hard to visualize so take
a look at the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://rwby.wikia.com/wiki/Penny&#39;s_Swords/Image_Gallery?file=Turnaround_1.png&#34;&gt;tournarounds&lt;/a&gt;
if you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what I mean. Without further ado&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blade-guard-and-grip&#34;&gt;Blade, Guard and Grip&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blade and grip needed to sit perfectly flush with the guard, and the
easiest way to fix parts that don&amp;rsquo;t quite fit together is &lt;a href=&#34;http://mattmunson.blogspot.ca/2007/11/bondo-squish.html&#34;&gt;The Bondo
Squish&lt;/a&gt;. This is a
very versatile technique, well worth keeping in your bag of tricks. The basic
idea is that you spread Bondo on one object, coat the other in something the
Bondo won&amp;rsquo;t stick to, and squish them together. Let the Bondo cure for an hour
or so and then you can separate them, clean up the squeeze-out and now you have
an inverse mold of one object in the surface of the other. I&amp;rsquo;ve also used this
trick to straighten up lines on parts by clamping them to the flat surface of
my workbench. In this case, I used regular scotch tape on the guard ring and
sprayed on a bit of old mold release. I had to repeat the process several times
for the joint between the blade and the guard to build up enough Bondo to fill
the entire gap, but in the end it worked out quite nicely. The steel rod in the
center of the blade provided good registration to keep the guard in the right
place each time. Once I was satisfied, I epoxied these three parts together
permanently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I was able to hold the sword by the handle - the steel core means
it&amp;rsquo;s quite able to support its own weight. That weight is considerable - MDF and
steel aren&amp;rsquo;t light. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to have to carry this around a convention
floor all weekend, but it works fine as a shelf piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-to-solder&#34;&gt;Learning to Solder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I knew I had to install the EL wire in the blade. In a perfect
world, I would have waited until after the painting was done, but this sword
has some parts that had to be constructed on top of the light diffusers, so that
wasn&amp;rsquo;t an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my EL Wire from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolneon.com/&#34;&gt;CoolNeon&lt;/a&gt;, and they live up to
their name. I made the rookie mistake of forgetting to order connectors to
attach the wire to the driver and they included four of them for free with a
nice note in the package. Shipping costs from California to Canada are pretty
rough, but the wire is tough, bright and easy to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar, EL wire works like this. You connect a battery to a
piece of electronics called a driver, which is then wired (either through
connectors or directly soldered) to the wire itself. Different drivers can
power different amounts of EL wire - I went with one of the smallest ones
because I wanted to hide the driver and battery inside the guard. CoolNeon
sells the wire pre-soldered, but that costs extra and I wanted to learn how to
solder anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out to be pretty easy. I bought a soldering iron, some solder and some
copper wire to practice on at my local hardware store, watched some YouTube
videos on soldering (good examples are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SQUiuyUY8pQ&#34;&gt;this one by
PunishedProps&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tsl5OW_w2JY&#34;&gt;this one by
CoolNeon&lt;/a&gt;). After a couple of
tries, I pretty much had it figured and I was able to complete the soldering
for the first two pieces of EL wire in about an hour.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-wire.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I glued the two strips of wire into the grooves on the blade with thin CA,
scuffed up the clear acrylic light diffusers with some sandpaper and glued
those in as well with epoxy. They didn&amp;rsquo;t sit quite flush owing to my mixup with
the groove depth earlier, but it&amp;rsquo;s good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;side-details&#34;&gt;Side Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sword has some extra little black- and copper-colored details on the side
of the blade where it folds in half to become a gun (Of course it&amp;rsquo;s also a gun.
Every weapon is RWBY is a gun somehow.) Of course, mine doesn&amp;rsquo;t transform but
it&amp;rsquo;s important to look as though it could. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t too hard. I used a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2ztH6bS&#34;&gt;plastic scoring knife&lt;/a&gt; and some chisel work to cut out
a couple of window shapes in 1mm styrene and glued them to solid squares of
thinner styrene with &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2zud33J&#34;&gt;Bondene&lt;/a&gt; (not to be confused with
Bondo. Great naming, folks). Then I cut a thin strip of 1mm styrene and, with a
lot of CA and filing, cut it into parts and made a continuous strip around the
middle of the blade. Then I glued on the square window-things I&amp;rsquo;d made.
Finally, I used a &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2ysJmS9&#34;&gt;razor saw&lt;/a&gt; to make a thin cut
through the styrene all the way around the blade to make it look like the blade
was segmented. At this point, everything was done and ready for paint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;painting-the-grip&#34;&gt;Painting the Grip&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the painting process by masking off the guard ring. I always use the
good (if expensive) &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2glSTnI&#34;&gt;Tamiya masking tape&lt;/a&gt; to start with
- I&amp;rsquo;ve found it works better at preventing leaks, handles curves better and
never pulls up paint. Of course, I&amp;rsquo;m also cheap, so I fill in the rest with
regular hardware store masking tape and paper towel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the grip, I went with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2xJEF7X&#34;&gt;plain grey primer&lt;/a&gt; as
the color for the raised sections (hey, if it works&amp;hellip;) and Montana Gold&amp;rsquo;s
Stealth Grey for the inner section (I&amp;rsquo;m not giving an Amazon link for that one
because the prices are outrageous. If you&amp;rsquo;re in Saskatoon, buy it from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artplacement.com/artstore/&#34;&gt;Art
Placement Art Supplies&lt;/a&gt; instead).
Montana Gold is good spray paint, but their cans tend to lay down very thick
coats that don&amp;rsquo;t dry very smoothly, so I prefer to decant the paint and spray
it through my airbrush instead. I use a &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2ysKIfH&#34;&gt;Model Master
B22&lt;/a&gt;, but to be honest that&amp;rsquo;s a lot more fancy than I
really needed - I got it on sale, but I&amp;rsquo;d recommend sticking with something
cheaper and simpler. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a good way to decant the paint except to
spray it by hand into a glass jar, so if you have any better ideas I&amp;rsquo;d love to
hear them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I coated the whole grip with the Stealth Grey, masked the inner
portion and added the light grey primer, but the cheap masking tape pulled up
the thin layer of stealth grey. Then I realized that I&amp;rsquo;d done it exactly
backwards. I coated the whole thing in light grey primer, masked out the raised
sections and added the stealth grey. After removing the masking tape and giving
the whole grip a coat of Montana Gold matte varnish (right from the can) I
moved on to the guard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;painting-the-guard&#34;&gt;Painting the Guard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guard of Penny&amp;rsquo;s sword is a bright orange copper color. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to
match it quite right (if you&amp;rsquo;re following along at home I&amp;rsquo;d suggest spraying
the copper on top of an orange-ish base coat) but it worked well enough I
guess. I started by wet-sanding the guard to 600 grit. Honestly, I probably
should have gone higher. For a convincing smooth-metal finish, you want even
the primer to be as smooth as you can get it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started by airbrushing on a couple of coats of &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2zfjBCf&#34;&gt;Alclad Gloss Black
Base&lt;/a&gt;. The glossy paint provides a smooth surface to
build the metal layer on. After that, I used &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2xK1LpX&#34;&gt;Alclad II
Copper&lt;/a&gt; for the shiny copper layer and &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2hKCWUS&#34;&gt;Alclad Aqua
Gloss&lt;/a&gt; for the clear coat. If you&amp;rsquo;re in Saskatoon, you
can buy all of these Alclad paints cheaper at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.expresshobbies.com/&#34;&gt;Express
Hobbies&lt;/a&gt;, but they&amp;rsquo;re often sold out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this worked quite well. I&amp;rsquo;m very pleased with the Alclad paints - they
spray well, cover well and look great. The Aqua Gloss does have a sort of
plastic-like texture to it that doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel as much like metal as the bare paint
does, but that&amp;rsquo;s a pretty small issue.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-copper.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;painting-the-blade&#34;&gt;Painting the Blade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blade has the most complex paint job of the build, but mostly because it has
a lot of small areas that needed to be done separately. To start with, the most
important bit is to avoid getting any paint on the acrylic light diffuser, so
I masked that off straight away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with a generous coat of stealth grey for the whole blade, again using
my airbrush to put down a finer coat than the spray can would have done. Volpin
Props&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.volpinprops.com/product/painting-and-weathering-for-props-and-replicas-ebook/&#34;&gt;Painting and Weathering for Props and
Replicas&lt;/a&gt;
book has a technique where you can bring up a bit of gloss on dark grey or black
matte paint by rubbing it with cloth covered in charcoal dust. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get it
to work here. Maybe I was using the wrong charcoal. Anyway, I left the sides of
the blade with the stealth grey and moved on to the edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another trick I learned from Volpin&amp;rsquo;s book is how to create a brushed-metal look
with Testor&amp;rsquo;s Buffable Metalizer lacquers. I&amp;rsquo;ll not give away the secret here
(Volpin&amp;rsquo;s book is well worth the 8$) but it worked beautifully. I used the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2zdoxYw&#34;&gt;Aluminum&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2yOUj1M&#34;&gt;Titanium&lt;/a&gt; shades
on top of the same Alclad gloss black as a base, then sealed it with the Metalizer
sealer. Other details on the blade were done with the same cast of colors and
techniques I&amp;rsquo;ve already mentioned - matte black primer for the styrene detils,
light grey primer for the end of the rail on the spine, gloss black, copper and
aqua gloss for the copper bits and aluminum metalizer for the little section
where the spine of the blade meets the guard. I did mistakenly mix the metalizer
with sealer rather than thinner for that last bit, but it seemed to work alright
anyway. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shine the resulting paint by buffing it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not a big
deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think I like the Alclad paints more than the Testors, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know
if the Alclad paints would work for the brushed-metal trick or not, so might be
best to have both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much weathering on this build because I wanted to match RWBY&amp;rsquo;s
bright and clean art style. I did a bit of silver dry-brushing around the line
between the brushed-metal effect of the edge of the blade and the dark grey of
the sides, but I think I did too much there. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to go too far with
dry-brushing, I find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;guard-covers&#34;&gt;Guard Covers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guard on Penny&amp;rsquo;s Sword has these complex little power-symbol icons on
either side. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t cut something that perfect by hand, so I used lasercut
MDF and acrylic. The power symbol is constructed out of a piece of MDF with the
symbol cut out, and two small pieces of acrylic to fit in those holes and a
larger acrylic ring to hold the power symbols and fit into the guard. These
power symbols have to light up, so they have EL wire inside as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with, I primed the flat rings, painted them stealth grey and
clear-coated them with matte varnish. The MDF power symbols were painted with
gloss black and clear-coated with aqua gloss. I set the power symbols face-down
on my workbench, slid the acrylic power-symbol parts into them and glued them
in place with hot glue. CA wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have worked well - it clouds the surface of
acrylic too much and would have run through the gaps and stuck everything to my
workbench - but ordinary hot glue was thick enough and clear enough to work just
right. I glued the power symbols to the guard covers with epoxy. I did have to
redo one of them twice due to mistakes (make sure everything is lined up before
you glue things together!) but I got there in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, it was smooth sailing. I hot-glued down some more EL wire to the
backs of the power symbols, soldered on the connectors and I was ready for final
assembly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-assembly&#34;&gt;Final Assembly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the sword was already together so this was limited to putting the guard
covers in place, hooking up the electronics and gluing on a couple of extra
bits. There is one thing to note though. Although I had enough space inside the
guard for the battery and driver (though I had to cut out part of the guard to
make room for the battery) I didn&amp;rsquo;t leave enough space for all of the wiring
and connectors. Sadly, I can&amp;rsquo;t actually close the guard with everything inside,
so I&amp;rsquo;ll have to leave some of the guts hanging out when I want to light it up.
Anyway, you probably want to see some pictures of the final result, so here you
go:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-finished.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;It looks positively Combat Ready!&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        It looks positively Combat Ready!
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-finished-glow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! This build took me about six months, but I had a lot of fun
with it and learned a ton of new stuff - soldering, lasercutting, airbrushing.
Whether you&amp;rsquo;re building your own replica of Penny&amp;rsquo;s Sword or just interested in
learning more about propmaking, I hope you found this useful. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Penny&#39;s Sword - RWBY - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 12:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll show you how I built a light-up replica of Penny Polendina&amp;rsquo;s
unnamed swords from Rooster Teeth&amp;rsquo;s excellent animated web show
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roosterteeth.com/show/rwby&#34;&gt;RWBY&lt;/a&gt;. RWBY is what originally got me
into propmaking - I&amp;rsquo;ve already made Yang&amp;rsquo;s Ember Celica shotgauntlets and
Adam&amp;rsquo;s Wilt &amp;amp; Blush Sword/Shotgun Combo. This is the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve documented
my process, so hopefully you find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blueprints-design&#34;&gt;Blueprints &amp;amp; Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a quick overview of how I intended to do this build. A lot of this plan
didn&amp;rsquo;t survive contact with reality, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s helpful to show where
things went off the rails. The plan was to make the blade out of two pieces of
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; MDF laminated together around a steel rod, to have a secure place to
attach the hilt and guard. The light-up detail along the blade would be done
with EL wire or LEDs covered by a thin layer of scratched-up acrylic glass to
diffuse the light. The other details on the blade would mostly be made of wood,
MDF and styrene. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how to cut or sand the bevel for the edge of the
blade, planning to figure that out when I got there. The guard was difficult -
it&amp;rsquo;s a more complex shape than it appears. It isn&amp;rsquo;t just a disk - the center is
dished in a bit. I also needed it to be hollow, since that&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;d put the
batteries and electronics to make it light up. The right way to do it is with a
lathe, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have a lathe or any idea how to use one. The hilt would also
be a challenge - it&amp;rsquo;s oval shaped, not round. I planned to cut it out of a
wooden dowel with a spokeshave and make the extra details out of styrene,
planning to fall back to 3D printing if that didn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I started by finding reference material and tracing out some
blueprints in Inkscape. Reference material for RWBY is usually pretty easy to
find, since Rooster Teeth often releases detailed turnaround shots of the
characters and their gear for exactly this purpose. The RWBY wiki features &lt;a href=&#34;http://rwby.wikia.com/wiki/Penny%27s_Swords/Image_Gallery&#34;&gt;a
number of images&lt;/a&gt; of
Penny&amp;rsquo;s swords, incuding detailed concept art and a &amp;lsquo;turnaround&amp;rsquo; which shows
the animation of the swords transforming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blade&#34;&gt;Blade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part I did last fall. I took a big block of &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; MDF to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://sktechworks.ca/&#34;&gt;local
makerspace&lt;/a&gt; and put it on the CNC mill. I came up with
some plan to use the manual control mode of the mill to cut the block into two
halves of the blade, which I would then glue together. I milled a &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; round
groove down the center of the inside of the blade to hold a steel rod for
reinforcement. Then I flipped each piece over and milled a second groove on the
outside of the blade for the light-up section. Unfortunately, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely
forgotten the exact process I used to do this so I can&amp;rsquo;t give more details.
I&amp;rsquo;ll take better notes next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward six months or so and it&amp;rsquo;s time to glue this thing together. I
scuffed up the in-sides of the MDF and the steel rod with sandpaper so the glue
would hold better and then covered it in wood glue and epoxy and clamped the
pieces together. This turned out to be a mistake. In my haste to get everything
together before the epoxy started to set, I didn&amp;rsquo;t line up the two parts
properly. They&amp;rsquo;re not even close. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time I&amp;rsquo;d make a costly
mistake with glues, either.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-shame.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Those lines should line up.&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Those lines should line up.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;D&amp;rsquo;oh. I also realized that the grooves I&amp;rsquo;d cut to hold the acrylic light
diffuser and EL wire are only 2-3mm deep - much too shallow to contain both the
2mm acrylic sheet and the 2.6mm EL wire. Double D&amp;rsquo;oh. I decided to attempt to
repair the damage rather than just starting over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I placed a wide chisel along the sides of the groove and tapped it lightly to
cut the fibers and prevent tearout while I cut the groove deeper. I then used a
quarter-inch chisel along the bottom of the groove to deepen it. Finally, I ran
a ball-end bit along the bottom using my rotary tool for the EL wire. That
worked&amp;hellip; less well, since it&amp;rsquo;s nigh-impossible to cut a straight line when the
tool itself is pulling to one side erratically. Fortunately, that part
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be easily visible so it&amp;rsquo;s OK. Finally, I marked a line around both
sides of the blade to show where the grooves shuld end and filled in the gaps
with Bondo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The edge bevel on Penny&amp;rsquo;s Sword is quite complex, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the same
angle along the length of the sword. I cut as much on my scrollsaw as I could.
Unfortunately, the sword is too long to fit entirely on the saw. In the end, I
hat to cut most of the edge bevel with a couple of hand files and a rasp. That
actually worked quite well. It took hours and a lot of elbow grease, but
there&amp;rsquo;s something satisfying about patiently working with hand tools until the
part is Just Right. If you plan to do this at home, be sure you know how about
Draw Filing. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, the idea is that you hold one end of the file in
each hand, press the center against the work and push it forward and draw it
back. I&amp;rsquo;ve found this technique to be much faster and more controllable than
filing along the length of the file using a sawing motion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-half-blade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once that was done, I spread some Bondo on some of the areas where I&amp;rsquo;d filed
too far and sealed the MDF with cyanoacrylate. Thin CA is best for this, as it
soaks deeper into the MDF, but my bottle of thin CA was so old that it turned
into thick CA all on its own. Regardless of the viscosity though, when the CA
hardens you&amp;rsquo;re left with a rough but hard and nicely sandable surface which
won&amp;rsquo;t soak up paint the way unsealed MDF does. It&amp;rsquo;s even wet-sandable, if done
carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that, plus some more sanding and spot-putty work, the blade was ready for
primer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blade-details&#34;&gt;Blade Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the half-round rail along the spine of the blade, I cut a piece of &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo;
dowel down the middle very carefully on my scroll saw, then cleaned it up by
rubbing the flat side of the now-half-round-ish dowel along a file. I glued
that down as straight as I could manage and cleaned up the seam with filler
primer, files and sanding twigs. For the larger half-cylindro-spherical (yeah,
I had to look that up) bit at the end, I cut a piece of &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; dowel in half and
cleaned it up as before, then used a sanding drum on my rotary tool to sculpt
the half-sphere part. This actually worked remarkably well. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get it
to be quite round enough with just the rotary tool, but some work with a
sanding sponge and filler primer got it close enough. The inner corners between
the two parts and the spine of the blade are hard to reach so they&amp;rsquo;re not as
clean as I&amp;rsquo;d like, but they&amp;rsquo;re probably good enough.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-spine.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are some additional details on either side of the blade, but those had to
wait. Those details are on top of the diffuser for the glowy sections on the
sides, which created an order-of-operations problem. I had to install the EL
wire and the diffuser before I could add those details, and then I had to paint
those detail bits and the rest of the blade after the diffuser was installed.
So I had to mask out the lens and try not to get any paint on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an oblong piece on either side of the blade where it meets the
guard. I intially tried cutting these out on my scroll saw and sanding them to
the right shape, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite get it right so I ended up just
laser-cutting them at the makerspace instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;guard&#34;&gt;Guard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh boy. This thing gave me so much trouble. As I mentioned above, I don&amp;rsquo;t have
a lathe and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know how to use one if I did. That means I really have two
options for making this piece. I could cut it on the CNC mill, or I could 3D
print it. I don&amp;rsquo;t really like either one (CNC milling is a hassle and 3D
printing is boring) but needs must. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had much experience on the CNC
mill at my local makerspace, and I&amp;rsquo;m proud to say that I&amp;rsquo;ve added a number of
shining new mistakes to that experience which I hope to not repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because this part had to be cut on both sides, I needed to be able to flip over
the work piece without actually moving it relative to the bed of the CNC
machine. In this case, this meant drilling a couple of holes through the
material into the sacrificial board on the bed of the machine, into which I
could place pieces of dowel. In theory, I could then flip the material over,
make sure the dowels are seated in their holes in the sacrificial board, and
carry on cutting on the other side. In practice, standard drill bits combined
with the much higher RPMs of the mill caused nasty tearout. Another piece of
sacrificial material on top of the workpiece would probably have helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This CNC machine doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a tool-changer, so I had to manually replace the
tool multiple times during the cut. To do that, you need to adjust the origin
for the height axis to reflect that the new tool is longer or shorter than the
old one. If you reset the other axes, though, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to finish the
cut, and that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what I did the first time. The second time, my work
piece came loose and I was informed that I had the movement speed of the CNC
router set far too high. Since this CNC machine is someone&amp;rsquo;s home-brew DIY
project, it&amp;rsquo;s somewhat lacking in documentation. Fortunately nothing was
damaged except my MDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having wasted several hours, damaged a couple cutting tools and destroyed two
blocks of MDF, I decided to just print it instead. This actually worked, which
is nice. It took a lot of sanding, puttying, priming and repeating before it
looked smooth enough, but I did get there in the end. I even printed in the
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; holes on either end to attach it to the rod inside the blade, though I had
to use a &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; rat tail file to open them up a bit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-guard.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The guard also has some other parts. First, some flat segments to turn the ring
into a complete guard, which I laser-cut from acrylic and then finessed a bit
with my files until they fit into the ring. Second, there are some sections
that are raised above the center of the guard and have a power-symbol design
that lights up. Those were also laser-cut from MDF and acrylic. All of these
small MDF pieces were filleted with a sanding sponge, sealed with CA and
primed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hilt&#34;&gt;Hilt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to all of that, the hilt was actually quite easy. I cut a couple of
sections of dowel to about twice the necessary length and took them to the
makerspace. After some failed experiments with the drill press, I asked a
couple of the guys there to help me with using the lathe to drill along the
center of the dowel. I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest - they did the work for me (thanks Al and
Scott!). Then I just cut the oversized dowel in half and had two hilt-sized
bits of wood which fit nicely on the &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;rdquo; rod extending from the blade. One
real one and a backup in case I messed up the first one. Helpful tip - always
make spares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had planned to try to use a spokeshave to cut the round dowel, but the
spokeshave was too dull to cut with when it arrived. I really ought to learn
how to sharpen blades. For now, though, I just clamped the dowel down in my
vice and went at it with my files and a sanding sponge. I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to find a more
versatile tool than my cheap set of hand files from Home Depot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hilt has a raised section on either end. Initially, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d heat up
some 1mm styrene, wrap it around and glue it in place. This didn&amp;rsquo;t work
(probably because I was trying to use a hair dryer and hot water. Maybe a heat
gun would have worked). After puzzling about it for a while, I came up with a
better idea. I cut a strip of thinner styrene which was flexible on its own.
Then I wrapped that around the hilt multiple times, using styrene cement to
glue each layer to the one beneath it like a roll of tape. This left an edge
where the styrene strip ended, but some filing and sanding blended that in
nicely. The styrene cement bonded the styrene to itself but not to the wood, so
I mixed a bit of epoxy and glued the two styrene end-caps to the dowel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all worked pretty well, but the two end-caps weren&amp;rsquo;t quite flush with the
sides of the hilt. I fixed that by scooping some baking soda into the gaps,
tapping it a bit to get it inside, and then scraping away the excess. With the
baking soda filling the gap, I dripped some thin CA (by this point I&amp;rsquo;d bought
a new bottle) inside. Baking soda causes CA to harden instantly and take up
more space than CA normally does, so this filled in the gaps nicely. A bit more
work with some needle files and sanding twigs to clean it up and it was ready to
go.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-hilt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is getting quite long, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to wrap up here. Almost all of the
parts are shaped, refined and primed. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/post/pennys-sword-rwby-part2&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain how I painted,
wired and finished the sword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what all of the pieces look like so far:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://bheisler.github.io/static/pennys-sword-parts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools-and-materials&#34;&gt;Tools and Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a short list of some of the tools and materials I used in this post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2ylNm5c&#34;&gt;Rustoleum Filler Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2xFPByh&#34;&gt;Plastruct Bondene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bondo &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2znGzrT&#34;&gt;Spot Putty&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2znHgRS&#34;&gt;Body Filler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2yokPO2&#34;&gt;Needle Files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://amzn.to/2ymxzmS&#34;&gt;Epoxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>